An Inventory of the Mary Ellen Leary Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Mary Ellen Leary Collection
1963-1984
87077
Leary, Mary Ellen
20 manuscript boxes (8.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Clippings, press releases, California state government publications, and other printed matter, relating to the political career of Ronald Reagan and to California state politics and government during his gubernatorial administration (1967-1974)
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives Audiovisual Specialist for further information.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1987
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Chronology
1913 April 21 Born, Salt Lake City, Utah
1934 Graduated from Duchesne College, an affiliate of Creighton University, Omaha, Nebraska Received a scholarship in English literature from Stanford University, California
1937 Completed M.A. from Stanford University
1937-1944 Reporter, San Francisco News
1944-1945 Political reporter
1945-1946 Nieman Fellow, Harvard University
1946-1952 Political editor
1952-1956 Urban specialist-Politics
1956-1964 Associate editor
1964-1967 West Coast correspondent, Scripps Howard papers
1966-1968 Member, Advisory Board, San Francisco Human Rights Commission
1968- Free-lance writer and correspondent, the Economist of London
1968-1974 Member, Oakland Catholic Social Justice Commission
1974-1975 Project director, Ford Foundation study, Candidate Media Interaction
1977 Author, Phantom Politics: Campaigning in California
1981 Author, A Journalist's Perspective: Government and Politics in California and the Bay Area: Oral History Transcript and Related Material, 1979-1981
1989 Received Distinguished Career Excellence in Journalism Award, Society of Professional Journalists, Northern California Chapter
Scope and Content of Collection
The Mary Ellen Leary collection focuses on the political situation in California during the 1960s through the early 1980s. The sources of information are published materials such as clippings and printed matter, press conferences and press releases, published government records, and speeches. They relate to Ronald Reagan's gubernatorial administration and to the development of his political career.
The guide to this collection has been prepared as an inventory. The papers listed are in their original order and topics added if given by the creator. Special mention has been made of articles by Mary Ellen Leary and letters addressed to her. This collection provides a valuable insight into California politics and Ronald Reagan's political aspirations.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
Reagan, Ronald.; California-Politics and government-1951.
Related Material
To see a complete listing of all the related collections, please go to Hoover Institution Archives catalog web site at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/ and use the search term Reagan, Ronald
Container List
- Reagan – Staff-Personnel, 1967. (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Clippings
- Reagan - Physical environment – Parks. (Folder 1: 2)
  Bulletins, clippings and printed matter, press releases, and speech, 1967
- Reagan programs, 1967. (Folder 1: 3)
  Clippings, correspondence, press release, printed matter, report, and writings
- Edmund G. Brown - Democrats, 1965-1970. (Folder 1: 4-5)
  Clippings and printed matter, memoranda, press release, publication, remarks, and statement
- Reagan, 1966-1968. (Folder 1: 6-7)
  Clippings, flyer, and press release. Includes a memoranda from Edmund G. Brown
- Reagan – Speeches and press conferences, 1966-1967. (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
  Includes press releases and report
- Reagan – Speeches and press conferences, 1967-1968. (Folder 2: 3-5)
  Includes announcements of appointments, press releases, and schedule
- Reagan – Appointments, 1967-1969. (Box-folder 3: 1-8)
  Press releases and announcements of bills passed
- Reagan – News clips, 1968. (Box-folder 4: 1-2)
  Includes press releases
- Reagan – Articles about him, 1967-1968. (Folder 4: 3)
  Includes clippings and printed matter and printed copy of a book about Ronald Reagan
- Reagan – Personal history, 1967. (Folder 4: 4)
- Reagan – States finance, 1966-1967 and undated. (Folder 4: 5)
  Clippings, report, and speech by George Miller, Jr.
- Reagan – California finance, 1966-1967 and undated. (Folder 4: 6)
  California tax study, message, report, and state budget
- Reagan, 1968. (Box-folder 5: 1)
  Budget message, press conference, and statement
- Reagan, 1968. (Folder 5: 2)
  Article, booklet, clippings, excerpts from speech, notes. press release, and statement
- Reagan – Press releases and speeches, 1968. (Folder 5: 3)
  Includes brochure, clippings, press conference, printed matter, and report
- Reagan – Appointments and announcements, 1968-1969. (Folder 5: 4)
  Clippings, report, and press releases
- Reagan - Politics, 1969. (Folder 5: 5)
  Includes correspondence, news clips, newsletter, note, press release, program, and schedule
- Reagan – Press conferences, press releases, and speeches, 1969 (Folder 5: 6-7)
- Reagan, 1970. (Box-folder 6: 1-4)
  Clippings, press releases, report, and schedule
- Reagan – Politics, 1970. (Folder 6: 5)
  Article by Mary Ellen Leary, press releases, report, and schedule
- Reagan, 1970 August – December. (Folder 6: 6-7)
  Clippings, press conferences, and press releases
- Reagan – Press releases, 1971 (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
- Reagan – Welfare, 1971. (Box-folder 8: 1-3)
  Article by Mary Ellen Leary, clippings and printed matter, press release, and report
- Reagan, 1969. (Folder 8: 4-5)
  Message, press conference, and press releases
- Reagan – Politics, 1971. (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
  Press releases and message
- Reagan, 1971. (Folder 9: 3-6)
  Clippings, press releases, maps of assembly districts, program, and report
- Reagan – Clippings, 1971 (Folder 9: 7)
- Annual reports, journals, and projects (Box 10)
  - Monthly Review, 1969 – 1971 February (Folder 10: 1)
  - San Francisco Business, 1971 March (Folder 10: 2)
  - Bank of America Annual Report, 1970. (Folder 10: 3)
    Includes notes
  - Wells Fargo Bank N.A. - "California: The Decade Ahead," fact book, 1970 April (Folder 10: 4)
  - Pacific Gas & Electric Company Annual Report, 1970 (Folder 10: 5)
  - Union Oil Company of California Annual Report, 1970 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Kaiser Industries Corporation Annual Report, 1970 (Folder 10: 7)
- Institute of Business and Economic Research, University of California, Berkeley - California Economic Forecasting Projects, 1969-1970 and quarters 1970 III through 1971 IV (Folder 10: 8)
- Reagan, 1972 June – December. (Folder 10: 9-11)
  Press releases, printed matter, and schedule
- Reagan - News clips, 1973 January – May (Folder 10: 12)
- Reagan – Appointments, 1972 January – December and; 1973 January (Box-folder 11: 1-2)
- Reagan – President, National Grand Old Party (Republican), 1967-1968. (Folder 11: 3)
  Clippings, excerpts from address, memoranda, and press release
- Reagan – Recall, 1968. (Folder 11: 4)
  Includes clippings, press conference, press release, and writings by Mary Ellen Leary
- Reagan – Minorities, 1967. (Folder 11: 5-6)
  Clippings, newsletter, press release, and report
- Reagan – Mental health, 1967-1968. (Folder 11: 7)
  Clippings, note, press release, printed matter, report, and speech
- Reagan – California economy, 1971-1972. (Box-folder 12: 1)
  Clippings, journal (Monthly Review, 1970 December), press release, report, and statement
- Reagan – Appointments, 1971-1972. (Folder 12: 2-4)
  Press releases, printed matter, program, and report
- Reagan, 1972 January – June. (Folder 12: 5)
  Messages and press releases
- Reagan – Appointments, 1971-1972. (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
  Press releases
  - Reagan, 1971. (Folder 13: 3)
    Clippings, excerpts of remarks, newsletter, and press releases
  - Reagan, 1972-1973. (Folder 13: 4-6)
  - Reagan, 1973. (Box-folder 14: 1-2)
    Press releases. Includes excerpts of remarks, and schedule
  - Reagan, 1974. (Folder 14: 3-5)
    Press releases - Appointments
- Reagan – Clippings, 1974 (Folder 14: 6-7)
- Reagan – Appointments, schedules, and press releases, 1974 (Box-folder 15: 1-6)
- Reagan, 1974. (Folder 15: 7)
  Clippings, message, press releases, and schedule
- Reagan, 1979-1980. (Box-folder 16: 1-2)
  Clippings and printed matter, letter, note, and press release mostly related to Hoover Institution
- Reagan – Post election, 1981. (Folder 16: 3-4)
  Miscellany
- Oakland Poverty Organization, 1970-1972. (Folder 16: 5)
  Clippings, letter, memoranda, notes, and press release
- Reagan – Welfare-Education-Mental Health, 1965-1967. (Box-folder 17: 1)
  Clippings, press release, and statement
- Reagan – News clips, 1971-1972 (Folder 17: 2)
- Reagan – California economy, 1969-1971. (Folder 17: 3)
  Correspondence including letters to Mary Ellen Leary, press release, printed matter, and report
- Reagan – Poverty, 1968. (Folder 17: 4)
  Clippings, memoranda, newsletter, press releases, and related materials
- Reagan – Miscellany, 1971. (Folder 17: 5)
  Clipping, press release, and printed matter
- Reagan – News clips, 1971 (Box-folder 18: 1)
- Reagan – 1980 campaign. (Folder 18: 2)
  Notes
- Regan – Republicans, 1970. (Folder 18: 3)
  Clippings, press release, report, and writings including by Mary Ellen Leary
- Reagan – Business – Finance Task Force, 1967-1968 and undated. (Folder 18: 4-5)
  Clippings, guide, letters to Mary Ellen Leary, press release, printed matter, report, and survey
- Reagan – Crime – Courts, 1967. (Folder 18: 6)
  Clippings, press release, remarks, and statement
- Reagan, 1967-1969. (Folder 18: 7)
  Clippings and press releases
- Reagan – Miscellany, 1964-1968. (Folder 18: 8)
- Reagan – Welfare, 1962-1972. (Box-folder 19: 1-5)
  Clippings, printed matter, and press releases
- Reagan – Welfare, 1971. (Folder 19: 6)
  Editorial and program
- Reagan – General, 1967-1969. (Box-folder 20: 1-3)
  Clippings, excerpts from speech, newsletter, press conference, press release, printed matter, and report and recommendations
- Reagan – President, 1984. (Folder 20: 4)
- Reagan – California Polytechnic Institute, 1971. (Folder 20: 5)
  Clippings, press releases, and printed matter